<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY testtable SYSTEM "test.xml">
<!ENTITY command_options SYSTEM "command_options.xml">
<!ENTITY config_settings SYSTEM "config_settings.xml">
<!ENTITY variables SYSTEM "variables.xml">
]>

<refentry>
	<refentryinfo>
		<address>
			<email>brenden1@users.sourceforge.net</email>
		</address>
		<author>
			<firstname>Brenden</firstname>
			<surname>Matthews</surname>
		</author>
		<date>2008-08-14</date>
	</refentryinfo>

	<refmeta>
		<refentrytitle>conky</refentrytitle>
		<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
	</refmeta>

	<refnamediv>
		<refname>conky</refname>
		<refpurpose>A system monitor for X originally based on the torsmo code, but more kickass.  It just keeps on given'er. Yeah.</refpurpose>
	</refnamediv>

	<refsynopsisdiv>
		<cmdsynopsis>
			<command>conky</command>
			<arg><replaceable>options</replaceable></arg>
		</cmdsynopsis>
	</refsynopsisdiv>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Description</title>
		<para>
			Conky is a system monitor for X originally based on torsmo.
			Since its inception, Conky has changed significantly from its predecessor, while maintaining
			simplicity and configurability.  Conky can display just about anything, either
			on your root desktop or in its own window.  Not only does Conky have many
			built-in objects, it can also display just about any piece of information by
			using scripts and other external programs.
		</para>
		<para>
			Conky has more than 250 built in objects, including support for
			a plethora of OS stats (uname, uptime, CPU usage, mem usage, disk
			usage, "top" like process stats, and network monitoring, just to name a few),
			built in IMAP and POP3 support, built in support for many popular
			music players (MPD, XMMS2, BMPx, Audacious), and much much more.
			Conky can display this info either as text,	or using simple progress
			bars and graph widgets, with different fonts and colours.
		</para>
		<para>
			We are always looking for help, whether its reporting bugs, writing patches, or writing docs.
			Please use the facilities at SourceForge to make bug reports, feature requests, and submit patches,
			or stop by #conky on irc.freenode.net if you have questions or want to contribute.
		</para>
		<para>
			Thanks for your interest in Conky.
		</para>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Compiling</title>
		<para>
			For users compiling from source on a binary distro, make sure you have the X development
			libraries installed.  This should be a package along the lines of "libx11-dev" or
			"xorg-x11-dev" for X11 libs, and similar "-dev" format for the other libs required (depending
			on your configure options).
		</para>
		<para>
			Conky has (for some time) been available in the repositories of most popular distributions.
			Here are some installation instructions for a few:
		</para>
		<para>
			Gentoo users -- Conky is in Gentoo's Portage... simply use "emerge app-admin/conky" for installation.
			There is also usually an up-to-date ebuild within Conky's package or in	SVN.
		</para>
		<para>
			Debian, etc. users -- Conky should be in your repositories, and can be installed by doing
			"aptitude install conky".
		</para>
		<para>
			Example to compile and run Conky with all optional components (note that some configure options may differ for your system):
		</para>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<command><option>sh autogen.sh</option></command> <option># Only required if building from SVN</option>
				</term>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<command><option>./configure </option></command><option>--prefix=/usr --mandir=/usr/share/man --infodir=/usr/share/info --datadir=/usr/share --sysconfdir=/etc --localstatedir=/var/lib --disable-own-window --enable-audacious[=yes|no|legacy] --enable-bmpx --disable-hddtemp --disable-mpd --enable-xmms2 --disable-portmon --disable-network --enable-debug --disable-x11 --disable-double-buffer --disable-xdamage --disable-xft</option>
				</term>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<command><option>make</option></command>
				</term>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<command><option>make install</option></command> <option># Optional</option>
				</term>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<command><option>src/conky</option></command>
				</term>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		<para>
			Conky has been tested to be compatible with C99 C, however it has not been tested
			with anything other than gcc, and is not guaranteed to work with other compilers.
		</para>
		<para>

		</para>
	</refsect1>



	<refsect1>
		<title>You Should Know</title>
		<para>
			Conky is generally very good on resources.  That said, the more you try to make Conky
			do, the more resources it is going to consume.
		</para>
		<para>
			An easy way to force Conky to reload your ~/.conkyrc: "killall -SIGUSR1 conky".
			Saves you the trouble of having to kill and then restart.  You can now also do the same with SIGHUP.
		</para>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Options</title>

		<para>Command line options override configurations defined in configuration file.</para>

		&command_options;

	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Configuration Settings</title>

		<para>
			Default configuration file location is $HOME/.conkyrc or
			${sysconfdir}/conky/conky.conf.  On most systems, sysconfdir is /etc,
			and you can find the sample config file there (/etc/conky/conky.conf).
		</para>
		<para>
			You might want to copy it to $HOME/.conkyrc and then start modifying it.
			Other configs can be found at http://conky.sf.net/
		</para>

		&config_settings;
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Variables</title>

		<para>
			Colors are parsed using XParsecolor(), there might be a list of them:
			/usr/share/X11/rgb.txt. Also, <ulink url="http://sedition.com/perl/rgb.html">
				http://sedition.com/perl/rgb.html</ulink>.
			Color can be also in #rrggbb format (hex).
		</para>

		&variables;
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Examples</title>
		<variablelist>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><varname>conky </varname><option>-t &apos;${time %D %H:%M}&apos; -o -u 30</option></term>
				<listitem>Start Conky in its own window with date and clock as text and 30 sec update interval.</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><varname>conky </varname><option>-a top_left -x 5 -y 500 -d</option></term>
				<listitem>Start Conky to background at coordinates (5, 500).</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

		</variablelist>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Files</title>
		<filename>~/.conkyrc</filename> default configuration file
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Bugs</title>
		<para>
			Drawing to root or some other desktop window directly doesn't work with
			all window managers. Especially doesn't work well with Gnome and it has
			been reported that it doesn't work with KDE either. Nautilus can be
			disabled from drawing to desktop with program gconf-editor. Uncheck
			show_desktop in /apps/nautilus/preferences/. There is -w switch in Conky
			to set some specific window id. You might find xwininfo -tree useful to
			find the window to draw to. You can also use -o argument which makes
			Conky to create its own window.  If you do try running Conky in its own
			window, be sure to read up on the own_window_type settings and experiment.
		</para>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>See Also</title>
		<para><ulink url="http://conky.sourceforge.net/">
				http://conky.sourceforge.net/</ulink></para>
		<para><ulink url="http://www.sourceforge.net/projects/conky">
				http://www.sourceforge.net/projects/conky</ulink></para>
		<para>
			#conky on irc.freenode.net
		</para>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Copying</title>
		<para>
			Copyright (c) 2005-2008 Brenden Matthews, Philip Kovacs, et. al.
			Any original torsmo code is licensed under the BSD license (see LICENSE.BSD for a copy).
			All code written since the fork of torsmo is licensed under the GPL (see LICENSE.GPL for a copy), except where noted differently (such as in portmon code, timed thread code, and audacious code which are LGPL, and prss which is an MIT-style license).
		</para>
	</refsect1>
	<refsect1>
		<title>Authors</title>
		<para>
			The Conky dev team (see AUTHORS for a full list of contributors).
		</para>
	</refsect1>
</refentry>
